<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>golang on Ilija Eftimov ⚡️</title><link>https://ieftimov.com/categories/golang/</link><description>Recent content in golang on Ilija Eftimov ⚡️</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Copyright 2022 © Ilija Eftimov</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ieftimov.com/categories/golang/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Four Steps to Daemonize Your Go Programs</title><link>https://ieftimov.com/post/four-steps-daemonize-your-golang-programs/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ieftimov.com/post/four-steps-daemonize-your-golang-programs/</guid><description>If you have ever worked with Ruby, or have maybe maintained a Rails application, I am sure the name Sidekiq will sound familiar. For those unfamiliar with the project, Sidekiq is a job system for Ruby. It is a wildly popular project, and the author has turned it into a successful business.
None of the above would be relevant if Sidekiq&amp;rsquo;s author Mike Perham, in 2014, did not write a concise and informative post titled &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t Daemonize your Daemons!</description></item><item><title>Understanding bytes in Go by building a TCP protocol</title><link>https://ieftimov.com/post/understanding-bytes-golang-build-tcp-protocol/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ieftimov.com/post/understanding-bytes-golang-build-tcp-protocol/</guid><description>Some of my newsletter subscribers have asked me a few times what is the easiest way to think about byte slices, or using Go&amp;rsquo;s syntax: []byte. Folks that have experience with low-level languages, where working with bytes is widespread, usually do not have challenges comprehending what []byte means and how to use it.
But, if you come from a dynamic or a high-level language background, although everything we do ends up being a bunch of bytes, higher-level languages hide such details from us.</description></item><item><title>My First dotGo Conference</title><link>https://ieftimov.com/post/my-first-dotgo-conference/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ieftimov.com/post/my-first-dotgo-conference/</guid><description>This year&amp;rsquo;s dotGo in Paris was awesome. The people were great in general. The organisers and volunteers did a good job. The attendees that I interacted with were cool – I had some interesting conversations and made couple of connections. The talks were informative and engaging. If this is where you stop reading, please give dotGo a shot next year - I am sure it will be great! And please find me in the crowd and talk to me, because I&amp;rsquo;d love to talk to you.</description></item></channel></rss>