<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>widget on Ilija Eftimov</title>
    <link>https://ieftimov.com/tags/widget/</link>
    <description>Recent content in widget on Ilija Eftimov</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2014 - 2019 Ilija Eftimov</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ieftimov.com/tags/widget/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Building a Weather Widget using RxJS</title>
          <link>https://ieftimov.com/post/build-weather-widget-rxjs/</link>
          <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          
          <guid>https://ieftimov.com/post/build-weather-widget-rxjs/</guid>
          <description>Reactive Programming is a very interesting programming paradigm that I started pondering with last week, which ended up in an article on this blog. Today, I will show you how you can write a very simple weather widget with reactive programming, using RxJS. Or, in other words, how to do HTTP calls in reactive programming fashion.
RxJS RxJS is an acronym for Reactive Extensions for JavaScript. Simply put, it is a set of libraries to do asynchronous and event-based programming using observable collections and iterators.</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Understanding Reactive Programming with RxRuby</title>
          <link>https://ieftimov.com/post/reactive-programing-rxruby/</link>
          <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          
          <guid>https://ieftimov.com/post/reactive-programing-rxruby/</guid>
          <description>Reactive Programming is a relatively new and interesting programming paradigm that has picked up quite a bit of popularity lately. Out of curiosity, I did a bit of research over the weekend. In this blog post I will summarize what I learned and try to explain what RP to any novice out there. Also, I show you how to use the Reactive Extensions for Ruby. Let&#39;s dive in!
The Motivation I rarely have strong opinions, but I really think that to understand anything in life, you need to understand the motivation behind it.</description>
        </item>
      
    
  </channel>
</rss>


