<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>golang on Ilija Eftimov</title>
    <link>https://ieftimov.com/tags/golang/</link>
    <description>Recent content in golang on Ilija Eftimov</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © Ilija Eftimov</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ieftimov.com/tags/golang/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
      
        <item>
          <title>My First dotGo Conference</title>
          <link>https://ieftimov.com/post/my-first-dotgo-conference/</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          
          <guid>https://ieftimov.com/post/my-first-dotgo-conference/</guid>
          <description>This year&#39;s dotGo in Paris was awesome. The people were great in general. The organisers and volunteers did a good job. The attendees that I interacted with were cool – I had some interesting conversations and made couple of connections. The talks were informative and engaging. If this is where you stop reading, please give dotGo a shot next year - I am sure it will be great! And please find me in the crowd and talk to me, because I&#39;d love to talk to you.</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Tell your team you are running late using Google Home, Google Cloud Functions, Golang and Twilio</title>
          <link>https://ieftimov.com/post/tell-team-running-late-google-home-google-functions-golang-twilio/</link>
          <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          
          <guid>https://ieftimov.com/post/tell-team-running-late-google-home-google-functions-golang-twilio/</guid>
          <description>In this age of cloud platforms, Internet of Things and SaaS products that are easy to integrate with, the effort of automating parts of your life is shrinking down substantially with every year that goes by. Additionally, these services have very generous free plans (or are quite affordable), you won&#39;t have to pay a fortune for this automation. In this article I&#39;ll show you how you can create your own commands for your Google Home.</description>
        </item>
      
    
      
        <item>
          <title>Barebones model of Spotify&#39;s &#39;Recently Played&#39; screen using a Least Recently Used (LRU) cache in Golang</title>
          <link>https://ieftimov.com/post/spotify-recently-played-least-recently-used-cache-golang/</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 11 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          
          <guid>https://ieftimov.com/post/spotify-recently-played-least-recently-used-cache-golang/</guid>
          <description>One of the most used caching schemes is Least Recently Used (LRU). Caches that use this eviction strategy will remove the least recently used item when their size reaches their capacity. That means that such caches have to keep a track of the order of access of the cached items, so it would evict the correct items.
Image taken from Undraw.  Before we go too much into details about the implementation of an LRU cache, let&#39;s first see what are the possible applications of this caching scheme.</description>
        </item>
      
    
  </channel>
</rss>
