<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>PostgreSQL on Ilija Eftimov</title>
    <link>https://ieftimov.com/categories/postgresql/</link>
    <description>Recent content in PostgreSQL on Ilija Eftimov</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ieftimov.com/categories/postgresql/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>PostgreSQL Indexes: B-Tree</title>
      <link>https://ieftimov.com/post/postgresql-indexes-btree/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ieftimov.com/post/postgresql-indexes-btree/</guid>
      <description>Indexes in relational databases are a very imporatant feature, that reduce the cost of our lookup queries. In the last post on the basics of indexes in PostgreSQL, we covered the fundamentals and saw how we can create an index on a table and measure it&amp;rsquo;s impact on our queries. In this post, we will take a dive into the inner workings and some implmentation details of the most used index type in PostgreSQL - the B-Tree index.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PostgreSQL Indexes: First Principles</title>
      <link>https://ieftimov.com/post/postgresql-indexes-first-principles/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ieftimov.com/post/postgresql-indexes-first-principles/</guid>
      <description>We have all heard about indexes. Yeah, that thing that it&amp;rsquo;s automatically added to the Primary Key column that enables fast data retrieval and stuff. Sure, but have you ever asked yourself if there are multiple types or implementations of indexes? Or maybe, what type of indexes your favourite RDBMS implements? In this blog post, we will take a step back to the beginning, exploring what indexes are, what is their role, types of indexes, metrics and so on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In and out of PostgreSQL using COPY</title>
      <link>https://ieftimov.com/post/postgresql-copy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ieftimov.com/post/postgresql-copy/</guid>
      <description>I am pretty sure everyone of us has been in a situation where you needed to generate a report and/or extract some data from a database and present it in a spreadsheet. In many cases, our clients prefer Excel to handle spreadsheets/reports, because, duh, it&amp;rsquo;s Excel.
So, how do you approach this problem? Do you copy and paste data? Or use a RDBMS GUI to generate the report into a spreadsheet?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>